Guide to the Richard Deming Papers, 1939-1988 and undated RL.11683
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard Deming papers
1939-1988 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Deming, Richard, 1915-1983
RL.11683
13.6 Linear Feet
Richard Deming (1915-1983) was an American crime and non-fiction writer. His papers primarily contain manuscripts by Deming, including short stories, novels, t.v. scripts and screenplays, publisher's pitches, along with plays, an article, poetry, and one letter. Some of the novels are written under the pseudonyms or with coauthors. All manuscripts are typescript, except for an incomplete, handwritten novel. The papers also include incomplete runs of mixed serials, all featuring published writing by Deming. These include scattered or single issues of each title and some duplicates. Items with dates past Deming's death in 1983 feature reprints as well as marketing materials for a novel. The collection also includes poetry and a novel-length manuscript written by Richard Deming's uncle, Rollin Gregg Deming.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Writings, Serials, and Rollin Gregg Deming.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Deming (1915-1983) was an American crime and non-fiction writer. Deming was born in Des Moines, Iowa, to Fred Kemp Deming and Eva Pearl (Smyers) Deming. His most common pseudonym was Max Franklin, although there were several others. He received his bachelor's degree from Washington University in St. Louis and a master's degree from the University of Iowa. Deming served in the U.S. Army in the European theater between 1941-1945 and became a captain. He married Ruth DuBois in 1948; the couple had three children.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Richard Deming Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift of John Betancourt in 2017.
Collection Overview
The Richard Deming papers primarily contain manuscripts by Deming, including short stories, novels, t.v. scripts and screenplays, publisher's pitches, along with plays, an article, poetry, and one letter. Some of the novels are written under pseudonyms or are co-authored. All manuscripts are typescript, except for an incomplete, handwritten novel. There are two folders containing research for novels and Deming's master's thesis is present. The papers also include incomplete runs of mixed serials, all featuring published writing by Deming. These include scattered or single issues of each title and some duplicates. Items with dates past Deming's death in 1983 feature reprints as well as marketing materials for a novel. The collection also includes poetry and a novel-length manuscript, The World of Snooze, written by Richard Deming's uncle, Rollin Gregg Deming.
American fiction -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; Crime in literature.; Detective and mystery stories, American; Deming, Richard, 1915-1983; Franklin, Max, 1915-1983; Deming, Rollin Gregg, 1887-1985
- Writings, 1939-1988 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes short stories, novels, t.v. scripts and screenplays, publisher's pitches, along with plays, an article, poetry, and one letter. Some of the novels are written under the pseudonyms Franklin W. Dixon, Lee Davis Willoughby, Frank Max or Max Franklin, with romance novels by Jessica or Charlotte Fen. Two novels are written with others, including Richard Laymon and Colleen Chandler, and there is a publisher's pitch written with Don Woodbeck and Craig Glazer. All writings are typescript, except for an incomplete, handwritten manuscript novel. There are two folders containing research for novels, and Deming's master's thesis is present. Items dating past Deming's death in 1983 include a reprint short story and marketing materials for a novel. There is an information folder for Deming located in box 1.
  - Short Stories, 1939-1988 and undated
    - ...Should be Points, not Craps, undated (Box 1)
    - The Awakening, undated (Box 1)
    - Birth of a Staff Section, undated (Box 1)
    - The Building of Jefferson Bates, undated (Box 1)
    - Cheers, undated (Box 1)
    - The Conventionalist, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - The Duelist, 1957 (Box 1)
    - A Doll with Eyes, undated (Box 1)
    - Early Fiction, undated (Box 1)
    - Encore, 1979 (Box 1)
      Publisher's pitch
    - Encore, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Four Minutes Fast, undated (Box 1)
    - Friendly Witnesses, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Go to the Ant, 1973; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - The Good Fairy, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - The Grand March, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Guardian of the Hearth, undated (Box 1)
    - Hangups, undated (Box 1)
    - High-level Courtship, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Holdover, undated (Box 1)
    - The House Hunter, 1975; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Human Sacrifice, undated (Box 1)
    - I Risked Happiness for Revenge, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - The Illusion of Reality, undated (Box 1)
    - The Love Master, undated (Box 1)
    - The Man Who Minded His Own Business, undated (Box 1)
    - Merest Tip of the Scales, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Writing, undated (Box 1)
    - Monster Brain, 1988 (Box 1)
      Reprint
    - Mother Love, undated (Box 1)
    - Natural Athlete, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Noble Gesture, undated (Box 1)
    - The Obsession, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Optical Illusion, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Patriotic Duty, undated (Box 1)
    - Possible Lead, undated (Box 1)
    - Rip Off, undated; 3 copies (Box 1)
    - Run for Your Life, undated (Box 1)
    - The Secret, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Sex and the Teenage Girl, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Sexual Athlete, undated (Box 1)
    - The Sign, undated (Box 1)
    - Six Little Mice Sat Down to Spin, undated (Box 1)
    - Speak to Deaf Ears, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - The Spellbinder, undated (Box 1)
    - They Can't Hang the Dead, undated (Box 1)
      Drafts
    - They Can't Hang the Dead, 1939 (Box 1)
      Master's Thesis
    - The Threadbare Cat and the Non-blooming Weed, undated (Box 1)
    - The Time Night Shirt, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Turnabout, undated (Box 1)
    - The Ultimate Singing Commercial, undated (Box 1)
    - Vicarious Hero, undated (Box 1)
    - What Would You Do with an Amphibrach, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - What You Feel in Your Mind, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - A Woman's Work, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Novels, 1964-1984 and undated
    - The American Girls, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
      under alias Max Franklin
    - Atomic Mystery, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The Avenger, undated (Box 7)
    - Barnstormer, about 1982 (Oversize-folder 1)
      Research
    - The Bounty Hunters, undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - The Bounty Hunters, 1984 (Box 7)
      Marketing materials
    - The Careful Man, 1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Original
    - The Careful Man, 1982; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Copy
    - The Civilians, undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - The Civilians, 1965?; 3 folders (Box 2)
      2nd draft
    - The Civilians, 1965?; 3 folders (Box 3)
      Carbon copy of draft 2
    - The Civilians, undated; 4 folders (Box 3)
      Final draft
    - Die Naked, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
      copy 1
    - Die Naked, a.k.a. 6-foot Nude, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
      Copy 1
    - Die Naked, a.k.a. 6-foot Nude, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
      Copy 2
    - The Fragging, 1981; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Grand Finale, about 1980 (Box 3)
      Outline
    - Grand Finale, about 1981; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Grand Finale, 1983; 3 folders (Box 3)
      #9
    - Grand Finale, undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
      House copy
    - Grownups, parts I and II, undated; 4 folders (Box 4)
      By Richard Laymon
    - Grownups, parts III and IV, 1983; 4 folders (Box 4)
      with Richard Laymon
    - Grownups, undated; 6 folders (Box 4)
      Revision notes
    - The Hardy Boys, undated (Box 4)
      Annotated
    - A Kiss Before I Die, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - One Violent Hour, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - One Violent Hour, 1964; 2 folders (Box 4)
      2nd version
    - One Violent Hour, undated (Box 4)
      3rd version
    - The Silent Service Series, 1980 and undated (Box 4)
    - The Smugglers, undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
      Revised pages
    - Son of Satan, 1980; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Original, under alias Frank Max
    - Son of Satan, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Draft 2, under alias Frank Max
    - Son of Satan, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Draft 3, under alias Max Franklin
    - Thieves of Chinatown, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
      under alias Franklin W. Dixon
    - The Torturers, undated (Box 5)
      Proposal
    - The Torturers, 1980; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - The Torturers, undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - The Unneeded, a.k.a. 1929, undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - The Unneeded, a.k.a. 1929, undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
      Fine copy
    - Untitled, incomplete handwritten manuscript, undated (Box 7)
    - The Upper Room, undated (Box 5)
      3 chapters plus outline
    - The Upper Room, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Publisher's Pitches, 1969?-1983 and undated
    - Depths of Danger, about 1980 (Box 2)
    - The Dungeons of Zanth, 1980 and undated; 5 copies (Box 2)
    - I saw My Daughter Dance, undated (Box 2)
      with Colleen Chandler
    - The Last Legend, undated (Box 2)
    - The Last Legend, undated (Box 2)
      Version 2
    - The Mainliners, 1969? (Box 2)
    - The Mainliners, undated (Box 2)
    - The Mystery of the Vanishing Pirate, undated (Box 2)
    - Outlaws, undated (Box 2)
    - Outlaws, undated (Box 2)
    - Outlaws, 1981 (Box 7)
    - The Replicas, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Schizophrenic, undated (Box 2)
    - Story Outlines and Plots, undated (Box 2)
    - The Suffragists, undated (Box 2)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 2)
      Incomplete
    - Yesterday's Love, undated (Box 2)
      under alias Charlotte Fen
  - T.V. Scripts and Screenplays, 1958-1983 and undated
    - Body Heat/The Drowning, 1983? (Box 1)
    - Body Heat/The Drowning, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Body Heat/The Drowning, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Body Heat/The Drowning, undated (Box 1)
      Draft 1, entitled Natural Causes
    - The Building of Jonathan Withers, undated (Box 1)
    - Dragnet: The Big Blackout, 1958 (Box 1)
    - The Girl from U.N.C.L.E.: The Velvet Voice Affair, undated (Box 1)
    - The Semi-perfect Wife, undated (Box 1)
    - Unfinished Scripts, undated (Box 1)
  - Plays, undated
    - Even If You Had Two Heads, undated (Box 1)
    - The Case of the Frustrated Corpse, undated; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Article, undated
    - Came the Revolution, undated (Box 1)
  - Poetry, undated
    - Poetry, undated (Box 1)
  - Letter, 1948
    - To Philip Lyman Deming II, 1948 (Box 1)
- Serials, 1948-1988
  Series contains incomplete runs of mixed serials, all featuring writing by Deming. There are scattered or single issues of each title and some duplicates. Issues with dates past Deming's death in 1983 feature reprints.
  - 5 Detective Novels Magazine, 1951 Summer (Box 9)
  - 15 Story Detective, 1950 August (Box 9)
  - Action-:Packed Western, 1955 November (Box 9)
  - Alfred Hitchcock's Anthology, 1981 Spring-Summer (Box 8)
  - Alfred Hitchcock's A Choice of Evils, 1983 Winter (Box 8)
  - Alfred Hitchcock's Mystery Magazine, 1957-1980 (Box 8)
  - Alfred Hitchcock's Shrouds and Pockets, 1988 Winter (Box 8)
  - Big-Book Western Magazine, 1951 November (Box 9)
  - Black Book Detective, 1953 Winter (Box 9)
  - Black Mask, 1948-1949 (Box 9)
  - Black Mask Detective, 1949-1951 (Box 9)
  - Bluebook, 1956 May (Box 10)
  - Bluebook Adventure in Fact and Fiction, 1952 September (Box 10)
  - [Complete] Detective Books, 1953 Summer (Box 9)
  - Detective Fiction Magazine, 1951 July (Box 9)
  - Detective Story Magazine, 1953 May (Box 9)
  - Detective Tales, 1950-1953 (Box 9)
  - Dime Detective Magazine, 1953 (Box 9)
  - Double-Action Detective, 1956 (Box 8)
  - Double-Action Western, 1953 July (Box 9)
  - Edgar Wallace Mystery Magazine, 1966 March (Box 8)
  - Ellery Queen Mystère-Magazine, 1956 March (Box 8)
  - Ellery Queen's Mystery Magazine, 1952-1967 (Box 8)
  - Ellery Queen's Mystery Magazine (Australian Edition), 1954 February (Box 8)
  - The Executioner Mystery Magazine, 1975 August (Box 8)
  - Exposed, 1956 April (Box 10)
  - Famous Detective Stories, 1953 (Box 9)
  - Fantasy Magazine, 1953 February (Box 8)
  - Fast Action Detective and Mystery Stories, 1957 January (Box 9)
  - F.B.I. Detective Stories, 1949-1950 (Box 9)
  - Fifteen Western Tales, 1951 November (Box 9)
  - For Men Only, 1957-1964 (Box 10)
  - Guy, 1964 December (Box 10)
  - I Gialli Di Ellery Queen, 1954 June (Box 8)
  - If, March 1953 (Box 8)
  - Intrigue Mystery Magazine, 1966 January (Box 8)
  - The Magazine of Fantasy and Science Fiction, 1951 October (Box 8)
  - Man's Magazine, 1962-1965 (Box 10)
  - Man's World, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
  - Manhunt, 1953-1962 (Box 8)
  - Manhunt, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
  - Mantrap, 1956 October (Box 8)
  - Max Brand's Western Magazine, 1951 November (Box 9)
  - Men, 1963 January (Box 10)
  - Mistério Magazine de Ellery Queen, 1954 November (Box 8)
  - Modern Man, 1967 February (Box 10)
  - Mr., 1956 July (Box 10)
  - Mystery Tales, February 1959 (Box 8)
  - The National Magazine, 1954 February (Box 10)
  - New Detective Magazine, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - O.K. for Men, 1959 June (Box 10)
  - Popular Detective, 1948-1951 (Box 9)
  - Posse, 1957 April (Box 10)
  - Private Eye, 1953 December (Box 8)
  - Pursuit Detective Story Magazine, 1956 March (Box 8)
  - Rex, 1957 December (Box 10)
  - The Saint Magazine, 1959-1984 (Box 8)
  - Salvo, 1957 January (Box 8)
  - Selecciones Ellery Queen de Crimen y Misterio, 1954 (Box 8)
  - Short Stories, March 1957 (Box 8)
  - Sir!, 1973 October (Box 10)
  - Smashing Detective Stories, 1952-1956 (Box 9)
  - Thrilling Detective, 1953 April (Box 9)
  - The Writer's 1956 Yearbook (Box 10)
  - Writer's Digest, 1956 March (Box 9)
  - Zane Grey Western Magazine, 1973 April (Box 10)
- Rollin Gregg Deming, 1980-1982 and undated
  Series contains poetry and a novel-length manuscript, The World of Snooze, written by Richard Deming's uncle, Rollin Gregg Deming.
  - Poetry, 1982 and undated (Box 6)
  - The World of Snooze, 1980; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - The World of Snooze, 1980; 2 folders (Box 6)
    Draft
  - The World of Snooze, undated; 2 folders (Box 6)